Cholera was reported in Haiti
تم التبليغ عن الكوليرا في هايتي
for the first time in over 50 years
لأول مرة منذ 50 عاما
last October.
أكتوبر الماضي.
There was no way to predict
لم تكن هناك أي وسيلة لتوقع
how far it would spread through water supplies
إلى أي مدى قد ينتشر في إمدادات المياه
and how bad the situation would get.
ومدى السوء الذي قد تصل إليه الأوضاع.
And not knowing where help was needed
وعدم معرفة أين احتيج للمساعدة
always ensured that help was in short supply
دائما يضمن أن المساعدة تكون ناقصة
in the areas that needed it most.
في المناطق التي تحتاجها أكثر.
We've gotten good at predicting and preparing for storms
قد صرنا جيدين في التوقع والإعداد للعواصف
before they take innocent lives
قبل أن تأخذ أرواحا بريئة
and cause irreversible damage,
وتسبب أضرارا لا رجعة فيها،
but we still can't do that with water,
لكن ليس بإمكاننا لحد الآن القيام بذلك مع المياه،
and here's why.
وهذا هو السبب.
Right now, if you want to test water in the field,
حاليا، إن أردتم اختبار المياه في الميدان،
you need a trained technician,
تحتاجون إلى تقني متدرب،
expensive equipment like this,
معدات مكلفة كهذه،
and you have to wait about a day
وعليكم الانتظار حوالي اليوم
for chemical reactions to take place and provide results.
حتى تحصل التفاعلات الكيميائية وتعطي النتائج.
It's too slow
من البطيء جدا
to get a picture of conditions on the ground
الحصول على صورة عن الوضعية في الميدان
before they change,
قبل أن تتغير،
too expensive to implement
مكلفة جدا لتنفيذها
in all the places that require testing.
في كل الأماكن التي تتطلب الاختبار.
And it ignores the fact that, in the meanwhile,
وتتجاهل حقيقة أنه، في هذه الأثناء،
people still need to drink water.
الناس لا يزالون يشربون الماء.
Most of the information that we collected on the cholera outbreak
جل المعلومات التي جمعناها حول انتشار الكوليرا
didn't come from testing water;
لم تأتي من اختبار المياه؛
it came from forms like this,
جاءت من استمارات كهذه،
which documented all the people
والتي وثقت كل الناس
we failed to help.
الذين فشلنا في مساعدتهم.
Countless lives have been saved
عدد لا يحصى من الأرواح تم انقاذه
by canaries in coalmines --
من طرف الكاناري في مناجم الفحم --
a simple and invaluable way
طريقة بسيطة ولا تقدر بثمن
for miners to know whether they're safe.
لعمال المنجم لمعرفة إن كانوا في أمان.
I've been inspired by that simplicity as I've been working on this problem
ألهمتني تلك البساطة وأنا أشتغل على هذا المشكلة
with some of the most hardworking and brilliant people I've ever known.
مع بعض أكثر الناس الذين عرفتهم اجتهادا وذكاء.
We think there's a simpler solution to this problem --
نعتقد أن هناك حلا أبسط لهذا المشكلة --
one that can be used
حل يمكن استخدامه
by people who face conditions like this everyday.
من طرف الناس الذين يواجهون وضعية كهذه يوميا.
It's in its early stages,
إنها في المراحل الأولى،
but this is what it looks like right now.
لكن هذا ما يبدو عليه حاليا.
We call it the Water Canary.
أطلقنا عليه كناري المياه.
It's a fast, cheap device
إنه جهاز سريع ورخيص
that answers an important question:
يجيب عن سؤال مهم:
Is this water contaminated?
هل هذا الماء ملوث؟
It doesn't require any special training.
وهو لا يتطلب أي تدريب خاص.
And instead of waiting for chemical reactions to take place,
وبدل انتظار حصول التفاعلات الكيميائية،
it uses light.
يستخدم الضوء.
That means there's no waiting
هذا يعني أنه ليس هناك أي انتظار
for chemical reactions to take place,
لحصول التفاعلات الكيميائية،
no need to use reagents that can run out
ليس هناك داع لاستخدام الكواشف التي قد تنفذ
and no need to be an expert
وليس هناك داع أن تكون خبيرا
to get actionable information.
للحصول على معلومات عملية.
To test water, you simply insert a sample
لاختبار الماء، تدخل بكل بساطة عينة
and, within seconds,
و خلال ثواني،
it either displays a red light, indicating contaminated water,
قد تعرض ضوء أحمر، يدل على مياه ملوثة،
or a green light, indicating the sample is safe.
أو ضوء أخضر، يدل على أن العينة آمنة.
This will make it possible
هذا سيجعل من الممكن
for anyone to collect life-saving information
لأي كان أن يجمع معلومات منقذة للحياة
and to monitor water quality conditions as they unfold.
ومراقبة وضعية جودة المياه وهي تنكشف.
We're also, on top of that,
ونحن كذلك، فوق هذا،
integrating wireless networking
ندمج شبكات لاسلكية
into an affordable device
في أجهزة في المتناول
with GPS and GSM.
من خلال محدد المواقع الGPS ونظام الهاتف المحمول GSM.
What that means is that each reading can be automatically transmitted to servers
ما يعنيه ذلك هو أنه كل قراءة يمكن أن تنقل أوتوماتيكيا إلى خوادم
to be mapped in real time.
ليتم تعيينها في الوقت الحقيقي.
With enough users,
مع عدد كاف من المستخدمين،
maps like this will make it possible
الخرائط كهذه ستجعل من الممكن
to take preventive action,
اتخاذ إجراءات احترازية،
containing hazards before they turn into emergencies
تحتوي على مخاطر قبل أن تتحول إلى حالات طارئة
that take years to recover from.
تتطلب سنوات للتعافي منها.
And then, instead of taking days
وبالتالي، وبدل استغراق أيام
to disseminate this information to the people who need it most,
لنشر هذه المعلومات على الناس الذي يحتاجونها أكثر،
it can happen automatically.
يمكن أن تحصل أوتوماتيكيا.
We've seen how distributed networks,
لقد رأينا كيف أن شبكات التوزيع،
big data and information
البيانات والمعلومات الضخمة
can transform society.
يمكن أن تحول المجتمع.
I think it's time for us to apply them to water.
أعتقد أن الوقت مناسب لنا لتطبيقها على المياه.
Our goal over the next year is to get Water Canary ready for the field
هدفنا في السنة المقبلة هو جعل كناري المياه جاهزا للميدان
and to open-source the hardware
وجعل الجهاز مفتوح المصدر
so that anyone can contribute to the development and the evaluation,
بحيث أن أي كان يمكن أن يساهم في التطوير والتقويم،
so we can tackle this problem together.
بحيث يمكننا معالجة هذا المشكل معا.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)